Edward Ellsberg Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Edward Ellsberg Papers 1891-2008 (bulk 1926-1998)
MSS86193
Ellsberg, Edward, 1891-1983
10,000 items
43 containers
17.2 linear feet
123 digital files (3.1875 MB)
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States Navy officer and author. Notebooks, correspondence, memoranda, lectures, articles, book drafts, short stories, play drafts, radio scripts, patents, military files, newspaper clippings, digital files, and other material relating to Ellsberg's service as an engineer and naval salvage expert. Also included are drafts and research files relating to John Doughty Alden's book entitled Salvage Man: Edward Ellsberg and the U.S. Navy.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Alden, John Doughty, 1921-2014. Salvage man: Edward Ellsberg and the U.S. Navy. 1998.; Ellsberg, Edward, 1891-1983.; Ellsberg, Edward, 1891-1983. Captain Paul. 1941.; Ellsberg, Edward, 1891-1983. Far shore. 1960.; Ellsberg, Edward, 1891-1983. Men under the sea. 1939.; Ellsberg, Edward, 1891-1983. No banners, no bugles. 1949.; Ellsberg, Edward, 1891-1983. On the bottom. 1929.; Ellsberg, Edward, 1891-1983. Passport for Jennifer. 1952.; Ellsberg, Edward, 1891-1983. Pigboats. 1931.; Ellsberg, Edward, 1891-1983. Thirty fathoms deep. 1930.; Ellsberg, Edward, 1891-1983. Under the Red Sea sun. 1946.; Ellsberg, Lucy Buck, 1893-1978. Lucy Buck Ellsberg writings.; Jones, John Paul. 1747-1792--Fiction.; Pollard, Edward Ellsberg, 1945- --Correspondence.
Organizations
Leviathan (Steamship); New York Naval Shipyard; S-51 (Submarine); United States. Navy--Officers.
Subjects
Marine engineering--United States.; Marine engineers--United States.; Mulberry harbors.; Salvage--United States.; Submarines (Ships); Submarines (Ships)--Fiction.; World War, 1914-1918--Fiction.; World War, 1939-1945--Africa.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Africa, North.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Eritrea--Mits'iwa.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--France--Normandy.; World War, 1939-1945--Europe.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations, American.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; World War, 1939-1945.
Occupations
Authors.; Naval officers.
Provenance
The papers of Edward Ellsberg, United States Navy officer and author, were given to the Library of Congress in 2017 by his grandchildren, Ann Pollard Heilakka and Edward Ellsberg Pollard.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Edward Ellsberg are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Digital Format
Digital files were received as part of the papers of Edward Ellsberg. Reference copies were created from the original digital media. Advanced notice is required for access to digital content; consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for more information.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1891, Nov. 12 Born, New Haven, Conn.
1910 Student, University of Colorado, Boulder, Colo.
1914 B.S., United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1914 1926 Officer, United States Navy
1918 Married Lucy Knowlton Buck
1920 M.S., Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Mass.
1926 1935 Chief engineer, Tide Water Oil Co., New York, N.Y.
1929 Promoted to commander by a special act of Congress for raising the sunken submarine, S-51 Published On the Bottom. New York: Dodd, Mead & Co.
1930 Published Thirty Fathoms Deep. New York: Dodd, Mead & Co.
1935 1941 Self-employed consulting engineer, New York, N.Y.
1938 Published Hell on Ice. New York: Dodd, Mead & Co.
1939 Published Men Under the Sea. New York: Dodd, Mead & Co.
1941 1951 Rejoined, United States Navy, and served as salvage officer in the Red Sea and western Mediterranean areas
1942 Published Captain Paul. New York: Dodd, Mead & Co.
1944 Participated in the Normandy invasion where he was instrumental in setting up artificial harbors off Normandy beach
1946 Published Under the Red Sea Sun. New York: Dodd, Mead & Co.
1949 Published No Banners, No Bugles. New York: Dodd, Mead & Co.
1951 Retired from the United States Navy as a rear admiral
1983, Jan. 24, Died Bryn Mawr, Pa.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Edward Ellsberg (1891-1983) span the years from 1891 to 2008, with the bulk of the material dating from 1926 to 1998. Ellsberg earned the reputation as one of the United States Navy’s premier experts on salvage operations and deep-sea rescue work. The collection, largely contained in notebooks, documents Ellsberg’s career as an officer in the United States Navy, his activities as a consulting engineer, and his authorship of articles and popular books relating to his salvage exploits while in the Navy and fictional writings about maritime topics. Also present are files relating to a 1998 biography about Ellsberg entitled Salvage Man: Edward Ellsberg and the U.S. Navy by John Doughty Alden, a few writings by Ellsberg’s wife, Lucy Buck Ellsberg, and correspondence of Edward Ellsberg Pollard, grandson of Ellsberg, regarding Ellsberg. The collection includes correspondence, memoranda, lectures, articles, book drafts, short stories, play drafts, radio scripts, notes, military papers, patents, notes, digital files, newspaper clippings, and printed matter. The papers are in English and are arranged as follows: notebooks, Salvage Man John Doughty Alden file, writings by Edward Ellsberg, and writings by Lucy Buck Ellsberg.
The notebooks are arranged by number and therein by topic or type of material. Documented in the notebooks are Ellsberg’s two tours of duty in the navy (1914-1926 and 1941-1951). Topics featured are his endeavors in solving the ventilation problems in 1924 of the steamer Leviathan while serving at the New York Naval Shipyard, in New York, New York, his successful salvage of the submarine S-51 in 1926, and his service during World War II at Mits'iwa in Eritrea, North Africa, and Normandy. During the Normandy invasion, Ellsberg used his expertise to create artificial harbors to facilitate the movement of supplies and troops. Other notebooks include files relating to his work as an engineering consultant, patents relating to his development of salvage equipment, his lectures, and his work as an author. Notebooks one through five, twenty-one, forty-five, and part of number seven, were not received by the Library.
Most of the notebooks, however, pertain to Ellsberg’s articles, books, short stories, book reviews, and correspondence about his writings. Books featured are On the Bottom (Ellsberg’s non-fiction account of the raising of the S-51), Under the Red Sea, No Banners, No Bugles, and The Far Shore (three non-fiction books about Ellsberg’s World War II service). Also present in notebooks numbered fifty-nine through sixty-two are drafts and correspondence about John Doughty Alden's biography Salvage Man: Edward Ellsberg and the U.S. Navy.
Other files complimenting the Salvage Man notebooks are paper and digital files of Ellsberg's biographer, John Doughty Alden. Alden gave his paper and digital files to Edward Ellsberg Pollard. Alden's papers include drafts, research files, and digital files that he used to write the biography and are filed under Salvage Man John Doughty Alden file. The digital files are word processing files received on five and a quarter inch disks. They include articles by Alden (based on his research for the biography prior to its publication), book drafts, and research material. Research material in the digital files consists mainly of notes, interview transcripts, outlines, and lists. The paper research files are larger and more substantive than the digital research files.
The majority of Ellsberg's book drafts, handwritten and typed, are filed near the end of the collection under writings by Edward Ellsberg. Papers pertaining to his fictional works include: Captain Paul (about John Paul Jones), Thirty Fathoms Deep (about a sunken submarine), and Pigboats (the basis for the movie Hell Below ). Non-fiction works represented in Ellsberg's writings are Men Under the Sea (a collection of salvage stories), Passport for Jennifer (Ellsberg’s endeavors to bring a young British orphan to the United States), On the Bottom (the salvage of the S-51), and those relating to his World War II service (previously mentioned in the notebooks). The writings also include drafts of plays, radio scripts, and short stories by Edward Ellsberg. Also included in the collection are a few writings by Ellsberg's wife, Lucy Buck Ellsberg. Pollard's correspondence about his grandfather is scattered throughout the notebooks, although notebook number sixty-three is exclusively such correspondence.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- Notebooks (Box 1)
  - No. 6, correspondence, 1928-2000, (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - No. 7, publisher, 1935-1980, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - No. 8, United States Navy, correspondence, and United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md., reunions, 1939-1980, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - No. 9, correspondence from divers and officers, 1926-1977, 1998-2003, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - No. 10, patents for torch, 1926-1943, 1957-1966, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - No. 11, patents for torch, pontoons, and evaporators, 1924-1968, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - No. 12, fan letters, 1932-1983, 1998, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - No. 13, lectures, 1926-1941, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - No. 14, lectures, 1941-1969, 1981, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - No. 15, story ideas, early unpublished stories, and Cleveland, Ohio, duty, 1929-1946, 1996, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - No. 16, articles, 1911-1930, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - No. 17, articles, 1931-1936, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 4, Box 5)
  - No. 18, articles, 1936-1955, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - No 19, articles, correspondence, articles about Ocean Gold, 1928-1936, 1954, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - No. 20, articles, correspondence, mostly New York Post, 1937-1941, 1955, 2005, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - No. 22, Leviathan (steamer), 1924-1926 (Box 6)
  - No. 23, professional engineering, 1935-1947, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - No. 24, professional engineering, 1947-1952, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - No. 25, professional engineering, 1952-1961, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - No. 26, orders, 1914-1940, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - No. 27, orders, 1941-1954, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - No. 28, Squalus (submarine) and sunken submarines, 1939-1940, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - No. 29, S-51 (submarine), salvage, 1925-1926, (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box 7, Box 8)
  - No. 30, S-51 (submarine), salvage, 1925-1938, 1986, 2008, (4 folders) (Box 8)
  - No. 31, On the Bottom, business, 1926-1931, 1973, 1985, 2000, (4 folders) (Box 8)
  - No. 32, On the Bottom, business, divers reunion party on Leviathan (steamer), and reception at Ambassador Hotel, New York, N.Y., 1929-1959, 1973, 1982, (4 folders) (Box 9)
  - No. 33, On the Bottom, business, correspondence, and fan letters, 1928-1931, 1955, 1996, (3 folders) (Box 9)
  - No. 34, On the Bottom, fan letters and reviews, 1925-1961, 1972-1976, 2004, (4 folders) (Box 9)
  - No. 35, promotion, 1926-1929, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - No. 36, proposed books and stories and reviews, 1928-1973, (3 folders) (Box 10)
  - No. 37, salvage proposals, diving and treasure, 1927-1967, (3 folders) (Box 10)
  - No. 38, S-4 (submarine), 1927-1939, 1949-1954, 2005, (1 folder); (3 folders) (Box 10, Box 11)
  - No. 39, North Africa and Normandy, 1942-1945, 2000, (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - No. 40, Mits'iwa, Eritrea, 1940-1946, (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - No. 41, Mits'iwa, Eritrea, 1940-1942, (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - No. 42, Mits'iwa, Eritrea, 1942-1959, 1992-2004, (5 folders) (Box 12)
  - No. 43, Thirty Fathoms Deep, Ocean Gold, Spanish Ingots, and Treasure Below, 1929-1961, (4 folders) (Box 12)
  - No. 44, Pigboats and S-54, 1929-1936, 1949-1952, 1978, 2005, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 12, Box 13)
  - No. 46, Hell on Ice: the Saga of the "Jeannette," business correspondence, 1935-1950, 1969-1971, (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - No. 47, Hell on Ice: the Saga of the "Jeannette," fan letters and correspondence, 1937-1953, 1961, 1969-1972, 2002, (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - No. 48, Hell on Ice: the Saga of the "Jeannette," reviews, 1938-1940, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 13, Box 14)
  - No. 49, Men Under the Sea and Cruise of the Jeannette, 1938-1957, (4 folders) (Box 14)
  - No. 50, Under the Red Sea, 1945-1947, (4 folders) (Box 14)
  - No. 51, Under the Red Sea, 1946-1970, 1980-1982, 1998, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 14, Box 15)
  - No. 52, No Banners, No Bugles, 1943-1955, (4 folders) (Box 15)
  - No. 53, No Banners, No Bugles, 1949-1959, 1980, (3 folders) (Box 15)
  - No. 54, Mid Watch: A Novel, 1951-1964, 1977, 1996, (3 folders) (Box 15)
  - No. 55, Captain Paul, 1939-1960, 1970, (4 folders) (Box 16)
  - No. 56, Captain Paul and "I have just begun to fight!" The Story of John Paul Jones, 1940-1958, 1981, 1990, (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - No. 57, Passport for Jennifer, 1948-1956, 1972-1980, 1991, (5 folders) (Box 16)
  - No. 58, The Far Shore, 1954-1968, 1977-1982, (3 folders) (Box 17)
  - No. 59, Salvage Man: Edward Ellsberg and the U.S. Navy by John Doughty Alden, draft, 1996, (4 folders) (Box 17)
  - No. 60, Salvage Man: Edward Ellsberg and the U.S. Navy by John Doughty Alden, draft, 1996, (2 folders) (Box 17, Box 18)
  - No. 61, Salvage Man: Edward Ellsberg and the U.S. Navy by John Doughty Alden, final draft, undated, (4 folders) (Box 18)
  - No. 62, fan letters and letters about Alden's biography, 1981-2004, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 18, Box 19)
  - No. 63, Edward Ellsberg Pollard, correspondence about Ellsberg, 1978-2003, (3 folders) (Box 19)
- Salvage Man: Edward Ellsberg and the U.S. Navy, John Doughty Alden file (Box 19)
  - Articles (Box 19)
    - Paper files, 1997-1998 (Box 19)
    - Digital files, 1996, mss86193_139_002
  - Drafts (Box 19)
    - Paper files (Box 19)
      - Original, 1996, (2 folders); (4 folders) (Box 19, Box 20)
      - Revised, undated, (3 folders); (2 folders) (Box 20, Box 21)
    - Digital files, 1994-1996, mss86193_139_001; mss86193_139_002; mss86193_139_003; mss86193_139_004; mss86193_139_005; mss86193_139_006; mss86193_139_007; mss86193_139_008; mss86193_139_009; mss86193_139_010
  - Fan letters, 1997-1998 (Box 21)
  - General, 1995-2006, (2 folders) (Box 21)
  - Grant, 1993-1996 (Box 21)
  - Publicity, 1997-2004, (2 folders) (Box 21)
  - Research file (Box 21)
    - Bibliography, 1998, undated (Box 21)
    - Biographies, 1947-1959, 1987, 1994-1995 (Box 21)
    - Boston, Mass., Navy Yard, 1920-1924, 1996-1998 (Box 22)
    - Christley, Jim, maps, 1996-1997 (Box 22)
    - Contemporaries, 1929-1940, 1994-1997, (2 folders) (Box 22)
    - Digital files: disparate files of outlines, notes and chronologies, interview transcripts, and lists, 1994-1996, mss86193_139_002; mss86193_139_006; mss86193_139_007; mss86193_139_011
    - Genealogy and early life, 1891-1996 (Box 22)
    - General, 1944, 1979, 1992-1997, (2 folders) (Box 22)
    - Index to book and related material, 1996 (Box 22)
    - King, Ernest J., and the Bureau of Aeronautics, 1933, 1995 (Box 22)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Mass., 1914-1936, 1969, 1995 (Box 22)
    - Mits'iwa, Eritrea (Box 23)
      - General, 1942-1946, 1975-1981, 1992-1996, (2 folders) (Box 23)
      - Letters, 1942, (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - McCloskey, Bruce B., and C. Monroe Hart, 1987, 1995 (Box 23)
    - "Midshipman cruise," 1911, 1995, (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - "Mulberry" harbors, 1944, 1995, 2007, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 23, Box 24)
    - New York Naval Shipyard, New York, N.Y. (Box 24)
      - General, 1916-1920, 1980-1981 (Box 24)
      - Leviathan (steamer), 1924-1926, 1939, 1980, 1995 (Box 24)
    - Niedermair, John C., interview, 1925-1926, 1975-1977, 1995 (Box 24)
    - Notes and related material, 1994-1996 (Box 24)
    - North Africa (Box 24)
      - General, 1942-1946, 1981, 1993-1994 (Box 24)
      - Letters, 1942-1943 (Box 24)
    - Orders, notes about, undated (Box 24)
    - Phoenix caissons and "NavEu" (Navy in Europe), 1944-1960, 1980-1981, 1991-1997 (Box 24)
    - Photographs (Box 25)
      - General, 1906-1920, 1933-1944, 1993-1998, undated, (4 folders) (Box 25)
      - Not used, 1911-1942, undated (Box 25)
    - Public Record Office, Great Britain, 1992-1995 (Box 25)
    - Resignation, 1926, undated (Box 25)
    - Retirement, 1945-1980, 1994, (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - S-4 (submarine) and Congress, 1926-1929, 1939, 1972, 1993-1997, (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - S-51 (submarine) (Box 26)
      - General, 1925-1926, 1979, 1993-1998, (2 folders) (Box 26)
      - Technical bulletin 2-27, 1927 (Box 26)
    - Searle, W. F., Jr., 1964, 1994-1999, (2 folders) (Box 26)
    - Service record and related biographical information, 1917-1924, 1938-1954, 1994, undated (Box 26)
    - Slides, circa 2004 (Box 26)
    - Sullivan, William A., 1947, 1954, undated (Box 26)
    - Supervisor of shipbuilding (Box 26)
      - Cleveland, Ohio, 1944-1945, 1994, undated (Box 26)
      - New York, N.Y., 1943-1950, 1980, 1995, undated (Box 26)
    - Tapes (audio) and notes, 1942, 1981-1982, 1994-1996, undated (Box 26)
    - Tide Water Oil Co. and other projects, 1929-1942, 1961, 1980, 1994-1996, undated, (1 folder) (Box 26, Box 27)
    - "To the Red Sea," 1941-1942, 1975, undated (Box 27)
    - United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md., 1910-1914, 1938, 1979, 1994-1995, undated (Box 27)
- Writings by Edward Ellsberg (Box 27)
  - Books (Box 27)
    - Captain Paul (1941), 1939-1940, (4 folders); (6 folders); (2 folders) (Box 27, Box 28, Box 29)
    - The Far Shore (1960) (Box 29)
      - First draft, 1958-1959, (4 folders); (1 folder) (Box 29, Box 30)
      - Revised draft, set A, undated, (3 folders) (Box 30)
      - Revised draft, set B, undated, (5 folders) (Box 30)
    - Hell on Ice: The Saga of the "Jeannette" (1938), circa 1937 (Box 31)
    - Men Under the Sea (1939), 1938, (8 folders) (Box 31)
    - Mid Watch: A Novel (1954) (Box 32)
      - First draft, 1952-1953, (4 folders) (Box 32)
      - Revised draft, undated, (3 folders) (Box 32)
    - No Banners, No Bugles (1949), 1948-1949, (6 folders); (4 folders) (Box 33, Box 34)
    - Ocean Gold (1935), 1934-1935, (3 folders) (Box 34, Box 35)
    - On the Bottom (1929), 1926, (5 folders); (2 folders) (Box 35, Box 36)
    - Passport for Jennifer (1952) (Box 36)
      - Ankers, Jennifer, 1948-1963 (Box 36)
      - First draft, 1952, (4 folders) (Box 36)
      - Revised draft, 1952, (2 folders) (Box 36)
    - Pigboats (1931), undated, (7 folders) (Box 37)
    - Spanish Ingots (1936), 1935, (5 folders) (Box 38)
    - Thirty Fathoms Deep (1930), 1929, (2 folders); (4 folders) (Box 38, Box 39)
    - Treasure Below (1940) (Box 39)
      - Drafts, 1939, (3 folders) (Box 39, Box 40)
      - Outline, notes, and other material, circa 1939-1940 (Box 40)
    - Under the Red Sea (1946), 1946, (4 folders); (6 folders) (Box 40, Box 41)
  - Play, S-54 (Box 42)
    - Handwritten draft, set A, undated, (5 folders) (Box 42)
    - Handwritten draft, set B, undated, (2 folders) (Box 42)
    - Various drafts, undated, (3 folders); (1 folder) (Box 42, Box 43)
  - Radio scripts, 1931-1936 (Box 43)
  - Short stories, 1935, undated, (2 folders) (Box 43)
- Writings by Lucy Buck Ellsberg, 1932, 1942, undated, (6 folders) (Box 43)